Guide to the Robert Southey Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert Southey collection
1797-1837
GEN MSS 298
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(1 box)
The collection consists of letters and writings by Southey. Included are letters to James Ballantyne, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, John May, James Montgomery, and Sir Thomas Noon Talfourd. Writings include manuscripts of Amadis de Gaula; The Curse of Kehama; Roderick, the Last of the Goths; and of Robin Hood, written with his wife, Caroline Southey.
Other Storage Formats: 6 volumes
Southey, Robert, 1774-1843
Southey, Caroline Bowles, 1786-1854
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Robert Southey, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to July 1997 have been organized into two series, Correspondence and Writings. Materials added to the collection since that time are located in Series III, Additions since July 1997, listed in the order in which they were added.
English poetry -- 19th century; Romanticism -- England; Ballantyne, James, 1772-1833; Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834; May, John, 1775-1856; Montgomery, James, 1771-1854; Southey, Robert, 1774-1843; Talfourd, Thomas Noon, 1795-1854
- Correspondence, [1809-10]; Series I
  - ALS to James Ballantyne, [Keswick], [1809-10] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Concerning Southey's work on the Edinburgh Annual Review
    Purchase, 1956
  - 2 ALS to Thomas Foster Barham, Keswick, 1816 Nov; 1817 Aug (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Purchase, 1957
  - ALS to Alfred Beesley, Keswick, 1824 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift, 1945
  - ALS to Mary Matilda Betham, Keswick, 1808 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchase, 1988
  - ALS to Joseph Bounden, Keswick, 1824 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Accompanied by engraved portrait of Southey
  - ALS to Sir Egerton Brydges, Keswick, 1830 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ALS to S.T. Coleridge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Purchase, 1970
  - ALS to Joseph Cottle, Bristol, 1799 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ALS to [Joseph] Cottle, Kingsdown, 1802 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift, 1950
  - ALS to Mr. Evans, Keswick, 1814 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ALS to William Gifford, 1816 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Gift, 1949
  - ALS to John Abraham Heraud, Keswick, 1828 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ALS to John Kenyon, Keswick, 1826 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 8 ALS to John May, 1799-1832 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Purchase, 1955
  - ALS to John May, Minehead, 1799 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ALS to [John May], 1803 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Accompanied by typescript
  - ALS to John May, [Keswick], 1807 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ALS to [John May], Keswick, 1830 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ALS to James Montgomery, Keswick, 1812 Oct 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Enclosed is a copy of Book II of his narrative poem Roderick, the Last of the Goths
    Gift, 1955
  - ALS to James Montgomery, [1817?] Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 7 ALS to James Montgomery, Keswick, 1811-30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - AL (with signature clipped off) to Mrs. [Mary Brent] Morgan, Keswick, 1826 Nov 30 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ALS to [John Murray]- concerning Washington Irving and a proposed life Jeremy Taylor, Keswick, 1822 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Signature cut out, and the name of Robert Southey has been inserted in another hand; at the top of the first leaf in the autograph of Washington Irving, is the note, "From Robert Southey to John Murray"
    Gift, 1925
  - ALS to Richard Parkinson, Keswick, 1833 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 2 ALS to Colonel Peachy, Keswick, 1810 Feb; 1810 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Embodying an epitaph in memory of "Emma.. .", i.e. Emma (Chartres) Peachy
    Purchase, 1939
  - Fragment of a note to Edward Quillinan, Keswick, 1830 Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Gift, 1961
  - 2 ALS to E.S. Rickman, Norwich, England, [1831] Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Accompanied with typescript dated 1835 May 15
  - ALS to Mr. Rumney, Newlands, 1819 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Gift
  - AL, signed with initials, to John Rumney, Keswick, 1824 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Written on subscription advertisement for his, A Chronological History of the West Indies, London, 1827
  - ALS to John Sheppard, Keswick, 1835 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 2 ALS to [Sir Thomas Noon Talfourd?], Keswick, 1834 Dec; 1835 Oct (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - ALS to W.B. Thomas, 1797 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Accompanied by a small piece of paper containing a note in Southey's hand on the words "Porrage or porridge, and pottage"
    Purchase, 1949
  - ALS to [Charles Benjamin Tayler], Keswick, 1833 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - ALS to H.T. [Henry Taylor?] in which is mentioned slavery and the growth of democracy in America, Keswick, 1820 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Signed "R.S."
    Gift, 1941
  - ALS to Richard Taylor, Keswick, 1829 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Gift, 1956
  - AL to Edith (Southey) Warter, Streatham, 1813 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Purchase, 1954
  - ALS to S. Wilkins, Keswick, 1831 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Accompanied with typescript
  - ALS to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, Keswick, 1837 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - ALS to Henry B., West Tarring, 1835 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Gift, 1957
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, 1799 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Purchase, 1958
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Keswick, 1811 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Keswick, 1818 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    He thanks him for sending some statements on the Peninsular War
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Keswick, 1822 Nov (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Gift, 1940
  - 2 ALS to unidentified recipients, [1823?] Dec; n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    2 engraved portraits of Southey enclosed
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Keswick, 1829 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Keswick, 1835 Oct (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Purchase, 1938
  - AL to unidentified recipient, [Keswick], 1837 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Gift, 1954
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - 2 MS extracts from letters, [1820,21] (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Accompanied by TLS from Kenneth Curry, Yale Ph.D. to Captain F.L. Pleadwell, former owner of the letters, Knoxville, Tennessee
- Writings, Series II
  - Amadís de Gaula. English translation: Southey, 1803
    "Amadis of Gaul," by Vasco Lobeira: autograph manuscript of Robert Southey's translation of a prose romance, from the Spanish version of Garci Rodríguez de Montalvo
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Volume 1
  - "Chimalpoca: A Monodrama Founded on an Event in the Mexican History" (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Autograph manuscript, signed "S" and endorsed "R.S.'s Autograph J.C."
  - "Commonplace Book", n.d.
    Autograph manuscript notebook containing miscellaneous notes, quotations, and some clippings, mainly on English literature and on Roman Catholicism
    See: Volume 2
  - AMs notes for "Cowper", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Purchase, 1964
  - "The Curse of Kehama", 1810
    Autograph manuscript, probably printers copy of the narrative poem; bookplates of James Cowan, Roderick Terry and Chauncey Brewster Tinker
    Gift, 1954 Tinker 1938A
    See: Volume 3
  - Autograph manuscript, signed, of the poem beginning: "Moments there are in life, alas how few!", Keswick, 1821 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Purchase, 1943
  - Nelson: Autograph notes on Admiral Horatio Nelson, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Purchase, 1971
  - Notes on his readings in English history: autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Notes on the life of Henry Kirke White: autograph manuscript, [1806-07] (Box 1, Folder 55)
    The notes are excerpts from the correspondence and commonplace books of White, whose memoir, written by Southey, was published in 1807
  - "Pierce Ploughman," AMs notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Gift, 1960
  - "Recollections of the Early Life of Robert Southey, Written by Himself in a Series of Letters to his Friend Mr. John May", [1821]-24 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Autograph manuscript of portions of the autobiography, including parts of letters VIII, IX, X, XIII, XV Purchase, 1953
  - Robin Hood
    Autograph manuscript poem, Part I (2 copies); manuscript of Part II by his wife, Caroline Southey, and in her hand; accompanied by Southey's notes for the story of Robin Hood, 1808 Oct 28-1814 Jul 19; paper watermarked 1822
    Purchase, 1960
    See: Volume 4
  - "Roderick, the Last of the Goths", [1814]
    Autograph manuscript copy made for the printer
    See: Volumes 5-6
  - "Roderick, the Last of the Goths": preface and other preliminary matter in the form of a letter addressed to James Ballantyne, the printer, 1814 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "Roderick, the Last of the Goths", [1812] (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Autograph manuscript of Book I of the narrative poem; title on ms: "Pelayo;" accompanied by photostats
  - "St. John Thrown into Boiling Oil", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Autograph manuscript poem, signed "Erthusyo"
  - "Seeds of Verse", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Autograph manuscript notes and outlines of ideas for verse; paper watermarked 1824
  - "Shadwell:" autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - "State of Ireland" (i.e. "Ode written after the King's visit to Ireland"): Autograph manuscript (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Written on several small pieces of paper, pasted together and mended; 11 stanzas, with parts of stanzas 5, 7 and 8 missing; accompanied with a picture and clipping containing biography
  - Miscellaneous manuscript fragments written in Southey's hand (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Accompanied by ALS from John Wood Warter to John A. Haslewood, dated 1856 Sep 24, concerning the manuscript fragments
- Volumes, 1803
  - Amadís de Gaula. English translation: Southey, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Commonplace Book", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Curse of Kehama", 1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Robin Hood (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Roderick, the Last of the Goths", [1814] (Box 1, Folder 5-6)